Department of Astrophysics Radboud University Nijmegen, The Netherlands ☑ rtprincy@gmail.com

Tahina Princy Ranaivomanana

PhD Candidate

rtprincy
trprincy
http://rtprincy.github.io

PROFILE

PhD candidate specialising in multi-wavelength time-series data analysis and machine learning applications in stellar astrophysics. Proficient in Python programming and deep learning frameworks (TensorFlow, PyTorch) for data modelling, time-series characterisation and classification. Published in peer-reviewed journals and experienced in international collaborations.

EDUCATION

Joint PhD candidate, Radboud University — KU Leuven	10/2021 — Present
MPhil in Astronomy, University of Manchester	2020 - 2021
M.Sc. in Astronomy, University of Antananarivo	2016 - 2017
B.Sc. Honours in Astrophysics, University of Antananarivo	2015 - 2016
B.Sc in Physics, University of Antananarivo	2012 - 2015

EXPERIENCE

PhD project 10/2021 — Present

Radboud University - KU Leuven

The Netherlands - Belgium

- Conducted unsupervised machine learning analyses with t-SNE and UMAP on Gaia DR3 multi-band lightcurves to identify and characterise the variability of \sim 1,500 hot subdwarf stars.
- Designed and implemented frequency analysis tool for sparsely sampled multi-colour lightcurves from MeerLICHT observations, achieving significant advancements in periodicity search.

MPhil project 09/2020 — 09/2021

University of Manchester

United Kingdom

 Developed semi-supervised GAN models for pulsar data synthesis and classification, aligning with large radio surveys (SKA).

Teaching Assistantship

•	Delivered tutorials for data analysis and astronomical instrumentation courses — Radboud University	2023 - 2024
•	Supervised 4 undergraduate research projects — KU Leuven	2022
•	Delivered tutorials for a Data Analysis course — Radboud University	2021

SKILLS

Programming	 Python: Conduct big data analysis with libraries such as Pandas, NumPy, SciPy, and Astropy SQL: Perform SQL query to retrieve datasets from astronomical databases Bash scripting: Automate task execution, job scheduling, and data pipeline management
Machine learning	 Familiar with Tensorflow, Keras, Pytorch libraries Perform classification, prediction, and clustering related tasks on tabular, time-series, and image data Deep learning: Perform synthetic data/image generation tasks for imbalanced learning
Astronomy software	 Topcat: TAP query, data manipulation, and visualisation MESA & GYRE: Perform basic modelling tasks Period04: Frequency search — pre-whitening tasks
Data handling	- Experience with large astronomical databases: BlackGEM, ZTF, TESS, Gaia

RELEVANT PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATION

- [1] P. **Ranaivomanana**, M. Uzundag, C. Johnston, et al. "Variability of hot sub-luminous stars and binaries: Machine learning analysis of Gaia DR3 multi-epoch photometry". In: *arXiv e-prints*, arXiv:2411.18609 (Nov. 2024), arXiv:2411.18609. DOI: 10.48550/arXiv.2411.18609. arXiv:2411.18609 [astro-ph.SR].
- [2] P. Ranaivomanana, C. Johnston, P. J. Groot, et al. "Identifying and characterising the population of hot sub-luminous stars with multi-colour MeerLICHT data". In: 672, A69 (Apr. 2023), A69. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202245560. arXiv: 2302.07266 [astro-ph.SR].

CERTIFICATION

Teaching training course: Offered by Radboud University (Online certificate)

Oxoford machine learning school certificate (Online certificate)

National Coordinator of Malagasy Astronomical Society (MAS)

Advanced Machine Learning and Signal Processing: Offered by IBM Skills Network (online certificate)

Data Analysis with Python: Offered by IBM Skills Network (online certificate)

Exploratory Data Analysis for Machine Learning: Offered by IBM Skills Network (online certificate)

PRIZES AND GRANTS

 Receipt of the Leids Kerkhoven-Bosscha Fonds (LKBF) grant (EUR 600) to attend the TASC/KASC 15 conference in Porto Receipt of the Leids Kerkhoven-Bosscha Fonds (LKBF) grant (EUR 500) to attend the Oxford machine learning school Receipt of the UK's Newton Fund/DARA Big Data MPhil Bursary Receipt of SKA/SARAO grant to attend the 2nd Big Data Africa School — South Africa 	2024 2023 2020 2018
 BlackGEM meeting (talk) — Manchester, United Kingdom KOPAL 2024 conference (flash talk) — Litomysl, Czech Republic TASC/KASC 15 conference (Poster) — Porto, Portugal Malagasy Astronomy Meeting (<i>Talk</i>) — Antananarivo, Madagascar AMCVn5 workshop (<i>Poster</i>) — Armagh, UK sdOB11 conference (<i>Poster</i>) — Armagh, UK MW-Gaia WG2 conference (<i>Talk</i>) — Sofia, Bulgaria TASC/KASC13 conference (<i>Poster</i>) — Leuven, Belgium sdOB10 conference (<i>Poster</i>) — Liege, Belgium 	2024 2024 2024 2023 2023 2023 2023 2023
EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES AND MEMBERSHIPS	
	2023 — Present — Present 2020 2018 2019

2019